Inventory of the Boris V. Prianishnikov papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Boris V. Prianishnikov papers
1921-1980
80156
Prianishnikov, B.
5 manuscript boxes (2.0 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Contains documents relating to the disappearance of émigré Russian generals A. P. Kutepov (1930) and E. K. Miller (1937) from Paris, Russian émigré anti-communist groups and Soviet penetration of them, the Narodno-Trudovoi Soiuz organization, White forces during the Russian Revolution, and Russian displaced persons after World War II. Consists of writings, correspondence, reports, and printed matter.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1980.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Boris I. Nicolaevsky collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Sergei L. Voitsekhovskii papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Petr Panteleimonovich Savin papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Narodno-trudovoĭ soiuz samizdat collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Russkiĭ obshche-voinskiĭ soiuz records, Hoover Institution Archives
Constantin W. Boldyreff papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical/Historical Note
1902 Born, Don Cossack territory, Russia
1913 Entered the Emperor Alexander III Don Cadet School in Novocherkassk
1917-1920 Participated in the Russian Civil War
1925 Immigrated to France
1933 Joined the Narodno-Trudovoi Soiuz (NTS)
1937 Author, Vnutrenniaia liniia
1938 Worked in Germany and Romania in various capacities, including writing, printing, and distributing NTS leaflets, brochures, and periodicals
1945 Established and became the first editor of Posev, the official organ of NTS
1947 Became the chief editor of Ekho (Regensburg, Germany)
1949 Emigrated to the United States
1949 Organized a New York section of NTS
1979 Author, Nezrimaia pautina
1986 Author, Novopokolentsy
Scope and Content of Collection
Upon immigration to the U.S. in 1949, Boris Vital'evich Prianishnikov became an American journalist and writer. His papers consist of selected research material collected for his two major books: Nezrimaia pautina (on Soviet infiltration of émigré organizations) and Novopokolentsy (on NTS).
The collection was arranged in 30 files by Boris Prianishnikov, and his folder titles and numeric filing system for research material has been retained. A typical file contains articles, clippings, notes, correspondents, and memoirs.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Kutepov, Aleksandr Pavlovich, 1882-1930.; Miller, Evgenii Karlovich, 1867-1937.; Anti-communist movements--Germany.; Propaganda, Anti-communist.; Refugees.; World War, 1939-1945--Refugees.; Espionage, Russian--France.; Russia--Emigration and immigration.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.
Collection Contents
- File 1. "Trest,", 1927-1980 (Folder 1: 1-8)
  Includes articles, notes, correspondence, and clippings
- File 2. "Skoblin i Plevitskaia,", 1921-1981 (Folder 1: 9-14)
  Includes articles, memoirs, notes, correspondence, and clippings
- File 3. "Trest" po N. Vinogradovu,", 1952-1963 (Folder 1: 15)
  Includes articles from Chasovoi, #321, 1952 and Pereklichka, 1962-1963
- File 4. "Vnutrenniaia liniia I. Main File,", 1930-1979 (Folder 1: 16)
  Includes memoirs, reports, correspondence, article, excerpts, and notes
- File 4. "Vnutrenniaia liniia I. Main File,", 1930-1979 (contd.) (Folder 2: 1-8)
- File 5. "Vnytrenniaia liniia II. Gallipoliiskii Vestnik, excerpts,", 1934-1960 (Folder 2: 9-10)
- File 6. "Vnutrenniaia liniia III. Proekt Beloi knigi" (Folder 2: 11)
  Includes excerpts from "Belaia kniga," by Mikhail A. Pavlov, copied by B. V. Prianishnikov in 1964
- Files 7-8. "Vnutrenniaia liniia IV. Petr P. Savin,", 1937-1978 (Folder 2: 12-16)
  Includes correspondence, article, and notes
- File 9. "Vnutrenniaia liniia V. Perepiska B. V. Prianishnikova s R. P. i A. A. Ronchevskimi,", 1958-1971 (Folder 3: 1-6)
  Includes clippings
- File 10. "Seriia statei v NRS, Gibel' generala E.K. Millera (K 25-vetiiu so dnia pokhishcheniia),", 1962 (Folder 3: 7)
  Includes correspondence and clippings
- File 11. "Vnutrenniaia liniia, Prilozheniia,", 1929-1955 (Folder 3: 8-12)
  Includes notes, drafts, printed matter, correspondence and clippings from Kseniia Denikina archives
- File 12. "Materlialy Igoria Konstantinovicha Martynovskogo,", 1927-1960 (Folder 3: 13-15)
  Includes notes, printed matter, correspondence, and clippings
- File 13. "General-leitenant E. K. Miller,", 1930-1979 (Folder 4: 1-3)
- File 14. "Affaire Miller I, 1937-1978. Doklad ot 27 dekabria 1937 goda s prilozheniiami, perevod s frantsuzskogo. Pozdneishie dopolneniia." (Folder 4: 4)
  Includes letters, article excerpts, and correspondence
- File 15. "Affaire Miller II. O roli Plevitskoi i o ROVS-e voobshche,", 1937-1957 (Folder 4: 5)
- File 16. "Affaire Miller III. Raport P. Tastevena, sekretaria sledstvennykh vlastei i drugie materialy,", 1921-1980 (Folder 4: 6)
  Includes article excerpts
- File 17. "Pokhishchenie na Generala A. P. Kutepova,", 1929-1984 (Folder 4: 7-10)
  Includes articles, notes, memoirs, correspondence, and printed matter
- File 18. "S. N. Tret'iakov. Mikrofony v kabinetakh gen. Millera i Vitkovskogo,", 1942-1983 (Folder 4: 11)
  Includes articles, clippings, and correspondence
- File 19. "General P. N. Shatilov,", 1927-1978 (Folder 4: 12-13)
  Includes notes, clippings, article excerpts, and correspondence
- File 20. "General F. F. Abramov,", 1937-1965 (Folder 4: 14-15)
  Includes article excerpts, clippings, and correspondence
- File 21. "Pokhishchenie na generala E. K. Millera Skoblinym,", 1937-1966 (Folder 4: 16)
  Includes article excerpts and clippings
- File 22. "Perepiska s G. E. Prilutskim,", 1960-1961 (Folder 5: 1-2)
- File 23. "Vnutrenniaia liniia, materialy iz arkhiva K. V. Denikinoi,", 1933-1938 (Folder 5: 3)
- File 24. "Kommissiia po delu Skoblina,", 1937-1963 (Folder 5: 4)
- File 25. "Perepiska s K. V. Denikinoi,", 1964-1971 (Folder 5: 5-6)
- File 26. "Materialy P. V. Makarova,", 1928-1970 (Folder 5: 7)
- File 27. "Aleksandr Amfiteatrov, Orden Iudy Predatelia, excerpts,", 1936 (Folder 5: 8)
- File 28. "N. N. Alekseev, sotrudnik redaktsii gazety Vozrozhdenie,", 1929-1974 (Folder 5: 9)
  Includes articles and clippings
- File 29. "Mladorossy-vtoraia sovetskaia partiia,", 1935-1973 (Folder 5: 10-13)
  Includes articles, correspondence, and printed matter
- File 30. Printed matter, 1939-1964 (Folder 5: 14)
  - 1. "Bol'shevitskie gangstery v Parizhe. Pokhishchenie generala Millera i Generala Kutepova," V. L. Burtsev, izdanie avtora, Paris, 1939 (Folder 5: 14)
  - 2. "Delo generala Lampe (sbornik dokumentov)," Vladimir Iugansen, Buenos Aires, 1961 (Folder 5: 14)
  - 3. "V bor'be za Rossiui, vospominaniia," general-leitenant V. K. Vitkovskii, 1963 (Folder 5: 14)
  - 4. "Vnutrenniaia Liniia (iazva na tele russkoi emigratsii)," Sao Paulo, Brazil, 1964 (Folder 5: 14)